Guide to the College of Optometry Records
University of Houston Libraries
College of Optometry Records
1950-2009
2009-013
University of Houston. College of Optometry
2.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
These records contain 2 boxes relating to the College of Optometry at the University of Houston. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant.
Historical Note:
The College of Optometry was established in 1952 by the Board of Regents as the result of a request from the Texas Optometric Association, which pledged to contribute $20,000 annually for operations. At the time of its establishment, the school was the only one in the South and the fifth in the nation to be established in connection with a university and with college entrance requirements. [1] Today, the school is one of only 17 optometry schools in the United States, and currently the only one in Texas. [2]
The College of Optometry, the University Eye Institute, and the Weston A. Petty Optometry Library are located in the J. Davis Armistead Building. Originally called the UH College of Optometry Building, constructed in 1976, the building changed names in 1993 to become the J. Davis Armistead Building in honor of Dr. Armistead’s dedication to the university and the profession. [3]
The teaching and research activities of the college are facilitated by the year-round operation of an outpatient clinic, the University Eye Institute, up-to-date research laboratories, an extensive library collection, a computer center, and instructional services. The College of Optometry offers the Doctor of Optometry (O.D.) degree and the Master of Science and Doctor of Philosophy degrees in physiological optics. [4]
References:
[1] Houston Post Article – “UH Optometry School Set Up; Professor Hired, February 20, 1952” (Box 1, folder 3)
[2] About UHCO, available from www.opt.uh.edu. 12 August 2009.
[3] About UHCO, available from www.opt.uh.edu. 12 August 2009.
[4] UH Through Time: Colleges, available from http://info.lib.uh.edu/sca/digital/time/index.html. 12 August 2009.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. College of Optometry.
Accruals:
Two folders of materials containing architectural plans were later added to the collection.
Five folders recounting the history of the College of Optometry were transferred by Suzanne Ferimer at the Optometry Library, May 30, 2014, and later added to the collection.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for Research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
These records contain 2 boxes relating to the College of Optometry at the University of Houston. A significant portion of this material was given to the archives from the university Print Plant. Materials include newsletters, correspondence, event programs and flyers, administrative material, published material, course information, reports, patient forms, and stationary. Included in this collection is a series of taped interviews. The collection is arranged chronologically and alphabetically as necessary. Material ranges in date from the 1950s to 2009.
Detailed List of Contents
- Printed Materials
  - undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - 1980s (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - "The Rehabilitative Optometry Journal", 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1990s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Spectacle", May 1990-July 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 2000s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - College of Optometry building bid, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - College of Optometry Architectural Plan, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Armistead Ranch Gathering, April 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ole Timers Retreat and UHCO History Recording Sessions, April 12-14, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History of the College of Optometry as Remember by Elizabeth MacNaughton, July 19, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "The Pheiffer Years" draft by Dr. Jim Koetting, July 26, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "An Anecdotal History of the University of Houston College of Optometry/Part II: The Pheiffer Years" by Dr. Jim Koetting, August 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Interviews with Famous Optometrists with Cassette Tapes
  - Dr. Charles Stewert by Bob Day, April 29, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Crawford Herron by B.J. Garner, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dr. Daniel Klaff by Harvey Sturdevant, August 26, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dr. Donald G. Pitts by Michael Poyner, May 9, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dr. Gordon W. McKee by Bob Joe, May 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dr. Lee Vann by Wes Wilkening, July 12, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dr. Lester Cheatham by Bruce W. Varner, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Dr. Lewis S. Bizer by H. Doug Baines, August 28, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dr. Max Levy by Steven D. Smith, April 24, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dr. Nelson Greeman Sr. by Tresy Greeman, April 27, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Pheiffer by Charles L. Stockwell (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dr. Phillip Lewis by Keith Manuel, May 1, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Dr. Robert Day by Bob Christensen, May 2, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Dr. Stanley Vogelfang by Jay S. Pravda, May 1, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dr. Weston Pettey by Steve Cowan, March 13, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)